Guide to the Alton Abraham Collection of Sun Ra 1822-2008
University of Chicago Library
Abraham, Alton. Collection of Sun Ra
1822-2008
156 linear feet (146 boxes, 1 oversize folder)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Alton Abraham (1927-1999), entrepreneur and hospital technician, was a longtime friend and business associate of Sun Ra (1914-1993), the influential jazz composer and musician. Alton Abraham collected manuscripts, business records, printed ephemera, artifacts, photographs, audio and video recordings, and other documents of his work with Sun Ra. The collection contains textual, graphic, and audio-visual records of the work of Sun Ra and his collaborators, as well as professional and personal papers of Alton Abraham. The collection spans 1822-2008, with material concentrated in the late 1950s-1980s.
Information on Use
Access
Series VIII: Subseries 2 and 3 do not include access copies for material in this series. Researchers must consult with staff before requesting material from this series.
Series XII contains personal financial records restricted for 50 years, and academic and medical records restricted for 80 years.
The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Sun Ra was born Herman Poole Blount on May 22, 1914 in Birmingham Alabama and was regarded as a skilled pianist and composer by his early teenage years. Although Blount based his musical activities in Birmingham until 1945, his big band toured extensively, playing Chicago in 1934 where he registered with the local musicians union under the name Sonny Blount. Blount read extensively, researching mystical and occult practices, ancient culture, biblical history, and contemporary developments in science and space exploration. During 1942-1943 he was imprisoned for draft resistance prior to being released with a 4-F classification.
In the winter of 1946 Blount migrated to Chicago, settling near Washington Park. Although regarded as eccentric by some, Blount was a respected and studied musician and was regularly employed as a pianist, composer, and arranger in the vibrant south side music scene. During the early 1950s he began rehearsing his own groups, ultimately leading to the 1955 creation of the Arkestra, the large ensemble he directed until his death in 1993. In October 1952 Blount legally changed his name to "Le Sony'r Ra" at the Circuit Court of Cook County, with "Sun Ra" serving thereafter as an abbreviated version of his new name.
Alton Abraham was born in Chicago on May 5, 1927. He served in the U.S Military in Okinawa from 1945-1947, and upon returning to Chicago in 1947 graduated from Du Sable High School, followed by Wilson Junior College in 1950. In 1952 he was certified as an x-ray technician at Provident Hospital. Blount and Abraham became acquainted in 1951, sharing interests in mysticism, the occult, science, numerology, and ancient history.
Along with Abraham's brother Artis, the men founded El Saturn Research in 1957, which would record and distribute albums by the Arkestra as well as the vocal and R&B groups rehearsed by Sun Ra during the late 1950s.
Additionally, Ra and Abraham organized Thmei Research, an organization dedicated to "subjects cosmic, spiritual, philosophical, religious, historical, scientific, economical, etc." Thmei also provided financing for El Saturn's earliest releases and issued a newsletter and book catalog. The earliest El Saturn recordings are singles dating from 1955 and 1956, including the Cosmic Rays "Dreaming" b/w "Daddy's Gonna Tell You No Lie." Some of the Arkestra's earliest studio recordings were released as Jazz By Sun Ra (1956) on Transition Records, and Super Sonic Jazz (1957) on Saturn Records.
In 1961 Sun Ra left Chicago for Montreal with members of the Arkestra including Marshall Allen and John Gilmore. Lacking sustained employment in Montreal, the group relocated to New York City where further difficulty finding work encouraged communal living arrangements. While Sun Ra would never again reside in Chicago, Abraham continued to manage some of the Arkestra's business engagements and the Saturn Record label in Chicago. By the late 1960s Sun Ra began giving performances on college campuses and appeared on the cover of Rolling Stone. During these years, recordings on ESP Records such as The Heliocentric Worlds of Sun Ra Vols. 1 and 2 (1965, 1966), added to the growing catalog of Sun Ra recordings available through Saturn Records such as The Magic City (1966) and Atlantis (1969). In 1967 Abraham, along with Sun Ra, James Bryant, and Almeter Hayden, incorporated Ihnfinity, Inc. in the State of Illinois with the intention of it serving as an umbrella organization for Sun Ra's activities. The following year Sun Ra and members of the Arkestra would move into a large home in the Germantown neighborhood of Philadelphia, commuting regularly to New York City for performances. In 1972 Ra and Abraham published two volumes of Sun Ra's poetry, The Immeasurable Equation, and Extensions Out: The Immeasurable Equation Vol. 2, some of which had previously appeared on the back cover of Saturn Records.
Opportunities for international performance expanded significantly during the 1970s and Arkestra recordings became more widely available following a 1972 agreement with Impulse Records, who reissued The Magic City and Atlantis in 1973. While Sun Ra would continue sending recordings to Abraham in Chicago through the late 1970s, such as The Soul Vibrations of Man (1977) and Taking a Chance on Chances (1977), he also began independently pressing Saturn records in Philadelphia, relying on the assistance of Arkestra members. Similarly, as performance opportunities expanded throughout the 1970s Arkestra trumpeter Danny Thompson increasingly took on the responsibilities of de facto business and tour manager.
Following Sun Ra's death in Birmingham 1993, Abraham became involved with the reissue and rerelease of out-of-print Sun Ra recordings. In addition to his activities with Sun Ra, Abraham was employed as an x-ray technician, and independently pursued his interests in spirituality, history, science, and technology. Alton Abraham died June 6, 1999 in Chicago.
Scope Note
Throughout his long friendship and business association with Sun Ra, Alton Abraham collected manuscripts, business records, printed ephemera, artifacts, photographs, audio and video recordings, and other documents. The collection contains textual, graphic, and audio-visual records of the work of Sun Ra and members of the Arkestra, as well as professional and personal papers of Alton Abraham. The collection spans 1822-2008, with material concentrated in the late 1950s-1980s.
This collection also contains material of research value in the subjects of audio and film recording, independent music production and distribution, African-American communities in Chicago, radical politics, health sciences, book collecting, race theories, spirituality and the occult.
There is considerable duplication of materials, particularly printed ephemera, across the collection. Copies of the same item duplicated in multiple series often document different aspects of Sun Ra and Alton Abraham's endeavors.
The collection is arranged in twelve series:
Series I: Biographical, contains writings about Sun Ra, including interviews, critical essays, articles, and obituaries. Also included in this series are a small number of biographical writings about John Gilmore.
Series II: Performance, contains textual and graphic documents of Sun Ra performances from 1966-1989, as well as performances by members of the Arkestra and other associated musicians from 1993-1998. Materials include clippings, broadsides, handbills, programs, press releases, set lists, and tour itineraries.
Series III: Recording, contains textual and graphic documents of recordings by Sun Ra, members of the Arkestra, and other associated musicians from 1955-1995. Materials include discographies, catalogs, clippings, press releases, handbills, broadsides, advertising copy, radio playlists, drafts of track listings and liner notes, and production notes.
Series IV: Music Manuscripts, contains Sun Ra's original works and arrangements of standards. Also included are music manuscripts prepared by others, including Alton Abraham. Materials in this series include arrangements, compositions, sketches, lyrics, notes and fragmentary music notations. Many of the manuscripts are undated, but generally range from the 1960s-1980s.
Series V: Verse, Prose and Notes, contains manuscripts, proofs, broadsides, pamphlets, notebooks and books by Sun Ra. It also includes notes, fragmentary works, and a small number of works by Alton Abraham and unidentified writers. Most items are undated, but generally span the 1950s-1980s.
Series VI: Business Records, contains records of the business operations of Saturn Records and other endeavors managed by Alton Abraham in collaboration with Sun Ra and others. The bulk of this material was kept by Alton Abraham, though some material may have been collected from Sun Ra, John Gilmore and others. Materials date from 1939-1998, but mainly document business activities from the late 1950s through the mid-1990s. Material in this series includes legal agreements, business forms and stationery, financial records, ephemera, instructional books and pamphlets, correspondence and notebooks.
Series VII: Alton Abraham, documents Abraham's education, employment, personal life, and interests in areas such as spirituality, the supernatural, science and technology, politics, history, and music. There is also some material related to Abraham's friends, associates and family members. Materials in this series include publications, ephemera, educational and instructional materials, correspondence, notes, sheet music, songbooks and manuscripts. This series spans 1822-1993, with material concentrated in the 1940s-1980s.
Series VIII: Audio-Visual, contains photographs, audio recordings, and film and video recordings. Included are photographs of Sun Ra and the Arkestra, filmstrips and videocassettes, audio cassette tapes, reel tapes, and vinyl records. Many items are undated, spanning the late 1950s-1990s.
Series IX: Art and Artifacts, contains items related to Sun Ra, Saturn Records, and music in general; as well as personal items that belonged to Alton Abraham. In the first category are sample album jackets; proofs and layouts of album covers, catalogs and advertisements; drawings, sketches and paintings; photographs of artworks; musical instruments and equipment; metal stampers for vinyl records; printing blocks and office supplies. In the second category are decorative ornaments and personal items such as a wallet and a briefcase.
Some items are matted or framed for display. Most items are undated but generally span the late 1950s-1980s.
Series X: Oversize, consists of large-format materials transferred from previous series.
Series XI: Restricted, consists of personal financial records, academic records, medical records, and identification and registration documents, all transferred from Series VII.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Chicago Jazz Archive
Subject Headings
Abraham, Alton; Sun Ra; University of Chicago. Chicago Jazz Archive; El Saturn Records; Jazz; Jazz musicians
INVENTORY
- Series I: Biographical
  This series contains biographical writings about Sun Ra, including interviews, critical essays, articles, and obituaries. Other biographical information includes a 1975 biographical statement, a postcard from the Hyde Park Art Center's "Pathways to Unknown Worlds" exhibition, a list of members of the Arkestra, and a map of Sun Ra's gravesite. Also included in this series are a small number of biographical writings about John Gilmore. Most of the writings in this series are in the form of clippings, photocopies, or sample copies of publications. This series is organized chronologically from 1966-2007, with undated material at the end of the series.
  Autobiographical writings by Sun Ra are in Series V: Subseries 1. Discographies are in Series III: Subseries 2. Oversize materials, consisting of newspaper clippings, a scrapbook, a Buzzard comic book, and a poster for the Hyde Park Art Center's 2006 symposium "Sun Ra: The Astro Black and Other Solar Myths," have all been transferred to Series X: Subseries 1.
  - "Homage to Sun Ra," Change, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Spiritual Voices of Black America," Liberator, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The New Jazz," Newsweek, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Henry Dumas, "An Interview with Sun Ra," Hiram Poetry Review, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tam Fiofori, "The Illusion of Sun Ra," Liberator, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Sun Ra," Jazz on Record, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John Sinclair, "Self-Determination Music," Jazz & Pop, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Harriet Choice, "Rah, rah...sunny Mr. Ra," Chicago Tribune, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ray Townley, "Sun Ra," Down Beat, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tom Bingham, "The Many Worlds of Sun Ra," Audio, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Harvey Pekar, "Sun Ra;" Vladimir Simosko, "John Gilmore," Coda, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Biographical statement, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bob Rusch, "John Gilmore: Oral history/Interview," 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bob Rusch, "Sun Ra: Interview," Cadence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - J.C. Thomas, "Sun Ra's Space Probe," Down Beat, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mark C. Gridley, "Bill Evans, Sun Ra, and Cecil Taylor," Jazz Styles, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Michael Hoenig, "Sounds: Tomorrow's Music Today," Penthouse, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Michael Hopkins, "Lord of the Saturnian Rings: Sun Ra Disco," The Spectrum, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Charles White, "The People are the Instrument: Interview with Sun Ra," Lightworks, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - David Miller, "Sun Ra," Real Times, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Une porte s'oeuvre," Les Tubes de l'Été, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Sun Ra's Solar Jet-Set Arkestra," Soho Weekly News, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Daniel Allen, "Sun Ra," Bibliography of Discographies, Volume 2: Jazz, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "International Jazz Critics Poll," Down Beat, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Sun Ra," New Musical Express, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Sun Ra," Stop, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Richard Harrington, "Jazz & Astral Visions," Washington Post, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Interplanetair entertainment met ceremoniemeester Sun Ra!" Travers, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Sun Ra," Nancy Jazz Pulsations, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - John Diliberto, "John Gilmore: Three Decades in the Sun's Shadow," Down Beat, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Val Wilmer, "John Gilmore: A Quiet Screamer from Mississippi," The Wire, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Art Sato, "John Gilmore," Be-Bop and Beyond, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Jim Macnie, "The Original Brother from Another Planet," The New Paper, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "The 52nd Annual Down Beat Reader's Poll," Down Beat, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Sun Ra," Jazz: The Essential Companion, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bob Doerschuk, "Sun Ra: Jazz from Another Planet," Keyboard, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Big Band," Down Beat, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Owen McNally, "Sun Ra: The high priest of avant-garde jazz," Hartford Courant, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Barry Kernfeld, "Sun Ra," New Grove Dictionary of Jazz, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Quotations from the Prime Minister of Saturn," 1988 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Ira Steingroot, "Sun Ra's Magical Kingdom," Reality Hackers, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sun Ra Omniverse Arkestra, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "All Over the Universe with Sun Ra," Record Exchange Music Monitor, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "Sun Ra," Wire Magazine, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Michael L. Lablanc, "Sun Ra," Contemporary Musicians, Volume 5, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Art Lange, "The First Evidence of Life on Saturn," Pulse! 1992 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Sun Ra, avant-garde jazz musician," Chicago Tribune, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Russell Woessner, "Joyful Memorial Tribute to Sun Ra with the Intergalactic Arkestra," City Paper, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - John Corbett, "Inherit the Sun," Down Beat, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Robert Campbell, "Sun Ra: Supersonic Sounds from Saturn," Goldmine, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Scott Yanow, "Sun Ra," Jazziz, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - David Block, "John Gilmore," Jazz Journal International, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Sun Ra," Life, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hyde Park Art Center, "Pathways to Unknown Worlds," 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - John Farris, "Space is the Place," undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tam Fiofori, "The Space Age Music of Sun Ra...'Between Two Worlds'," undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tam Fiofori, "Sun Ra's Space Odyssey," undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jim Macnie, "Sun Ra is the Heaviest Man in this Galaxy," undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jim Macnie, "Space is the Place," undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Harvey Pekar and R. Crumb, "Ridin' the Dog," undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bret Primack, "Captain Angelic: Sun Ra," Down Beat, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bryan Sale, "Sun Ra," Be-Bop and Beyond, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Michael Shore, "Sun Ra," undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - David Sprague, "Sun Ra Not of this Earth," undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Neil Tesser, "Sun Ra's wild orbit cooks hot dish," undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Rich Theis, "Sun Ra," undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Astro Black Mythology," Forces in Motion, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "The Free, New Jazz of Sun Ra," undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Sun Ra," undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Sun Ra," Jazz Pianists, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Sun Ra celestiali suoni del futuro," undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Sun Ra and his Solar Astro-Infinity Arkestra," undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - List of Arkestra members, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Map of Sun Ra's gravesite, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Jazz Store Catalog, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series II: Performance
  This series contains textual and graphic documents Sun Ra performances from 1966-1989, as well as performances by members of the Arkestra and other associated musicians from 1993-1998. Also included is material documenting the film Space is the Place. Materials include clippings, broadsides, handbills, programs, press releases, set lists, and tour itineraries. This series is chronologically by performance date. Performance dates are given as identified on the items. Undated items are at the end of the series.
  Oversize broadsides, newspaper clippings, and posters (including several large-format posters for concerts and the film Space is the Place), been transferred to Series X; Subseries 2. Photographs, audio recordings, and film and video recordings of performances are in Series VIII. Some material in this series is duplicated in Series VI.
  - Tompkins Square Amphitheater, New York, 14 July 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Slugs', New York, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - University of Santa Clara, Santa Clara, California, 11 April 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - London and Paris, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 2 February 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Alhambra Theater, San Francisco, 13 November 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The East, 29 December 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Auditorium Theater, Chicago, 21 April 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Black Music Conference, Amherst College, Amherst, Massachusetts, April 1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mexico tour, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Keystone Korner, San Francisco, 30 October-10 November 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Ruthie's Inn, Berkeley, California, 30 November-1 December 1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - San Francisco Art Institute, San Francisco, 19 April 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Maryjane, Sacramento, California, 3 May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified festival, 17 July 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Venue, London, 27-28 July 1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jazz Marathon, Brussels, 1-3 June 1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Carnegie Hall, New York, 20 September 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Ann Arbor Jazz Festival, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 28-30 September, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Glasgow International Folk Festival, Glasgow, Scotland, July- August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bluebird, Bloomington, Indiana, 11 October 1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Paris Jazz Festival, Paris, 25 October-1 November 1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - European tour, March 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - The Old Waldorf, Fans Francisco, 4 April 1984 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 1 October 1985 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Joe Segal's Jazz Showcase, Blackstone Hotel, Chicago, 1-6 October, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Seattle, 7 January 1986 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Grendel's Lair, Philadelphia, 4 August 1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Club Lingerie, Los Angeles, 24 September 1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Sweet Basil, New York, 30 June-5 July 1987 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Center Fest, North Carolina, 18-25 September 1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Harmonie Park, Detroit, Michigan, 17 October 1987 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Bastille Days, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 15 July 1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Club Quattro, Japan, 8 August 1988 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Chicago Old Style Jazz Festival, Chicago, 31 August-4 September 1988 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Staller Center, New York, 28 February 1989 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Koncepts Cultural Gallery, Oakland, California, 7-8 April 1989 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Sant'Anna Arresi Jazz Festival, Sardinia, Italy, August-September 1989 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - D.C. Space, Washington, D.C., circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Presidential Jazz Weekend, Philadelphia, 12-15 February 1993 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - First Congregational Church, Washington, D.C. (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Afro-American Historical and Cultural Museum, Philadelphia,18 October 1993 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Fez, New York, 4 January 1998 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Community Education Center, Philadelphia, 18 January 1998 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Jake and Oliver's, Philadelphia, 14 February 1998 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - West Warwick, Rhode Island, 15 July 1998 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Bright Monuments Festival, University of Massachusetts-Amherst, 18 July 1998 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Vermont Jazz Festival, Brattleboro, Vermont, 19 July 1998 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - "The Jazz City," Philadelphia, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Budland, Chicago, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Ella Guru's, Knoxville, Tennessee, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Brooklyn Academy of Music, Brooklyn, New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Unidentified Pan-African Study-Tour Committee performance, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Haverford College, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Series III: Recording
  This series contains textual and graphic documents of audio recordings by Sun Ra and members of the Arkestra from 1955-1995. This series is organized into two subseries:
  Subseries 1: Production and Promotion, is organized chronologically by item date or by recording release date. Item dates sometimes differ from release dates. Undated items are at the end of the series. Materials include catalogs, clippings, press releases, handbills, broadsides, advertising copy, radio playlists, drafts of track listings and liner notes, and production notes.
  Subseries 2: Discographies, is organized chronologically by document date. This subseries contains discographies compiled by researchers of Sun Ra's work, as well as by Alton Abraham. Discographies are in the form of notes, lists, photocopied articles and printouts of computer files.